Guide to the New York University Department of History Oral History Class Collection OH.033
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- Series I. Lower East Side Oral History Project Interviews, 1991-1994; 7 Linear Feet in 1 record carton, 4 media boxes, and 8 card catalog drawers; 0.75 Linear Feet in one record carton; 4 videocassettes (hi8); 4 videodiscs (dvd); 192 sound discs (cd); 133 audiocassettes
  - Taube, Ruth, 1991 October 11; 478408 (Box 1, Folder 107, Box 12, Cassette 39A-39B, Box 4, Cd 11-12)
    Ruth Taube was born in the Jewish Maternity Hospital in the Lower East Side neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. Her parents immigrated to the United States from Austria-Hungary. Taube had two brothers. Taube married and had at least one daughter. At the time of the interview, Taube was the director of the Henry Street Settlement's Home Planning Workshop.
    This interview was conducted on October 7, 1991 by Elizabeth Nichols and Ulrike Daehnhardt at the Mayor Fiorello H. LaGuardia Houses in the Lower East Side (LES) neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. The interview was continued on October 11, 1991 by Nichols at the Vladeck Houses in the LES. The interview covers Ruth Taube's work at the Henry Street Settlement's Home Planning Workshop in the LES and her life in the LES. Taube describes her introduction to the Henry Street Settlement's Home Planning Workshop, first as a temporary sewing instructor and the way in which she became a permanent employee of the Settlement. She discusses changes in the Workshop from the time she started to the time of the interview and explains the importance of the Workshop and the Settlement to the residents of the LES. She describes her childhood and her family's apartment in the LES. She describes her parents, their immigration experiences, and their working lives in the United States. She describes her family's apartment in the LES. She discusses her childhood memories of the Settlement and the activities held at the Settlement. She describes the summer camp at Camp Echo Hill in New Jersey and its importance to the residents of the LES who were able to attend the camp. Other topics include the participants in the Workshop, the ways in which the Settlement cooperation between the different ethnic and racial groups in the LES, her relationship with Helen Hall, and the development of the Vladeck Houses.
    Duration: 1:34:41
  - Varon, Rose Camhy, Undated (Box 1, Folder 108)
    Rose Camhy Varon was born in 1911 in the Lower East Side (LES) neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. Her family was Jewish and her parents immigrated to the United States from Turkey. Her father worked as a tailor and her mother managed the household. Varon was a member of the Congregation Shearith Israel on Eldridge Street and the University Settlement in the LES.
    The audio recording for this interview is missing. Currently all that is available is the preliminary questionnaire completed by Rose Camhy Varon, which contains only the biographical information recorded in the Biographical Note.
  - Weinstein, Beverly Fischer, 1993 June 3; 478456 (Box 1, Folder 109, Box 14, Cassette 89A-89B, Box 5, Cd 25-26)
    Beverly Fischer Weinstein was born into a Jewish family in 1935 in the Lower East Side neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. Her parents immigrated to the United States (US) from Poland in the early 1900s. Her maternal grandfather was the schochet, or ritual slaughterer, for the Jewish community of Newark, New Jersey. In 1923, Weinstein's parents married and moved to the Williamsburg neighborhood of Brooklyn. Her father managed a wholesale leather business in the Lower East Side (LES) neighborhood of Manhattan. After the birth of her eldest brother, the family moved to an apartment on Henry Street in the LES. After the death of her father when Weinstein was two years old, her mother managed the business and raised her five children. Between 1937 and 1955, the family lived in a three bedroom apartment on Madison Street in the LES. She earned her bachelor's degree in sociology and psychology from City College in Manhattan. Weinstein worked as a psychiatrist at Elmhurst Hospital in Queens. During her 20s, Weinstein travelled and worked in Israel for a few years, before returning to the US and working at Columbia-Presbyterian Clinic located in Upper Manhattan. She married in 1964 and had children. The family moved to the Fresh Meadows neighborhood of Queens, where she lived at the time of the interview.
    This interview was conducted on June 3, 1993 by Sylvia Groen at an unspecified location. The majority of the interview covers Beverly Fischer Weinstein's childhood experiences being raised by her widowed mother in the Lower East Side (LES) neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. She vividly describes the family's apartment on Madison Street in the LES apartment and the fact that it was an entire floor of the building and a railroad style apartment. Weinstein discusses the fact that their apartment was near her family's leather business. She discusses her friends' reactions to her apartment and to the LES and their comparisons between the LES and the neighborhoods in which they lived in upper Manhattan. Weinstein recalls visiting the Educational Alliance and being a member of the Young Israel Synagogue of Manhattan. She discusses the importance of family; weekly Sunday visits from relatives who lived in Newark, New Jersey; and her participation in many weddings. She expresses pride in her education and work experiences and explains that she was glad she waited until she was about 30 years old to get married. Weinstein states that she enjoyed her independence and argued that it allowed her to gain meaningful experiences which she might not have been able to have if she had gotten married and started a family at an earlier age.
    Duration: 1:58:25
  - Weiss, Jack, 1994 February 21; 478470 (Box 1, Folder 110, Box 15, Cassette 103, Box 6, Cd 3)
    Jack Weiss was born into a Jewish family in 1925 in Manhattan, New York. His father immigrated to the United States from Austria-Hungary in 1905 and his mother was born in Jersey City, New Jersey. He had one sister. Weiss lived in the Lower East Side (LES) neighborhood of Manhattan, where his parents managed the apartment building in which the family lived. When Weiss was 13 years old, the family moved to the Bronx. He attended Public School 188 and Stuyvesant High School in Manhattan. He worked as a salesman and a teacher, and was a member of the Workmen's Circle. Weiss married and had children.
    This interview was conducted on February 21, 1994 by Dawn Vander Vloed at an unspecified location. The interview covers Jack Weiss's childhood and family. Weiss describes his family's apartment in the Lower East Side neighborhood of Manhattan, New York and his parents' responsibilities as the managers of the apartment building. He discusses the culture of the neighborhood, including the food one could purchase from food vendors on the street, and relations amongst the different ethnic groups in the neighborhood. He describes the food his mother and grandmother would make and discusses the culture surrounding baking for the Jewish sabbath in the neighborhood. Other topics include Weiss's military service during World War II and discipline in his family.
    Duration: 1:07:59
  - Weiss, Mendel, 1994 February 22; 478471 (Box 15, Cassette 104, Box 1, Folder 111, Box 6, Cd 4)
    Mendel Weiss was born into a Jewish family in 1923 in Germany. Both of his parents died at the Auschwitz concentration camp in Poland, and his only brother died at an unspecified concentration camp. In 1941, Weiss was imprisoned in a Russian labor camp. Weiss immigrated to the United States in 1953. He lived with his uncle in the Lower East Side neighborhood of Manhattan, New York before moving to the Williamsburg neighborhood of Brooklyn. Weiss's first job was in a leather jacket factory on Hester Street in the Lower East Side. He later worked for his uncle, who was a wholesaler and distributor of underwear. Around 1960, Weiss opened his own wholesale and retail shop on Orchard Street in the Lower East Side.
    This interview was conducted on February 22, 1994 by Lori Finkelstein at Mendel Weiss's store at 91 Orchard Street in the Lower East Side neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. The majority of the interview covers Weiss's immigration experience, his experience owning a business, and his opinions on differences in the Lower East Side between the1960s and the time of the interview. Weiss discusses the difficulties he faced getting his immigration papers. He remembers having to travel around Russia for the required documents and physical examination. Weiss recalls purchasing the space that became his wholesale and retail business. He states that the ethnic demographics of the neighborhood had changed from predominantly Jewish and Eastern European in the 1960s to Chinese and Hispanic at the time of the interview. Weiss shares his opinion that the growth of department stores in the Lower East Side has increased at the time of the interview and was hurting local businesses.
    Duration: 01:00:48.
  - Weitzman, Anne Bramnick, 1993 May 5; 478457 (Box 14, Cassette 90, Box 1, Folder 112, Box 5, Cd 27)
    Anne Bramnick Weitzman was born in 1908 in Russia. She immigrated to the United States with her family in 1913. Her family was Jewish and she had four brothers. The family settled in the Lower East Side neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. Her father worked as a cooper and as a peddler, and her mother managed the household. She married and was a member of the Workmen's Circle, Branches 146 and 137E in New York City.
    This interview was conducted on May 5, 1993 by Minta Plotkin at Anne Bramnick Weitzman's home in the Kingsbridge neighborhood of the Bronx, New York. The interview covers Weitzman's early life in Lower East Side (LES) neighborhood of Manhattan. Weitzman discusses her immigration experience and describes her family's apartments in the LES, including the living arrangements, ways in which the family members negotiated privacy for themselves, and amenities and utilities in the apartment. She recalls using public baths on Allen and Rivington Streets in the LES. She discusses family and friends visiting on the weekends and food her mother would cook. She describes stores and vendors on Orchard Street where her family would shop and an ice cream shop at which she would meet friends. She discusses different streets in the neighborhood and what products were produced and sold on each street. She discusses illnesses in her family and two doctor services to which her mother subscribed. She discusses her membership in the Workmen's Circle, different programs in which she was involved, and activities in which she participated.
    Duration: 45:37
  - Williams, Farrell, 1994 April 25; 478472 (Box 1, Folder 113, Box 15, Cassette 105A-105B, Box 6, Cd 5)
    Farrell Williams was born in 1952 in the Lower East Side neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. His mother was born in Hattiesburg, Mississippi and his father was born in New Orleans, Louisiana. Shortly after their marriage, they migrated to New York and settled in the Lower East Side neighborhood of Manhattan on Grand Street. After high school, Williams worked in a film development lab and as a freelance photographer. He joined the United States Merchant Marine and was a member of the Seafarers' International Union of North America, Atlantic, Gulf, Lakes, and Inland Waters District.
    This interview was conducted on April 25, 1994 by Kerrie C. Cotten at an unspecified location. Farrell Williams discusses his parents' decision to migrate from New Orleans, Louisiana to the Lower East Side neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. He recalls his father's opinions about living in the northern United States (US) versus the southern US. Williams remembers his paternal grandmother living with the family on Grand Street and how his mother took care of her as she had diabetes. Williams talks about shopping in the Chinatown neighborhood of Manhattan in the 1960s and recalls experiencing racial discrimination. He recalls attending an Ike and Tina Turner concert at the Apollo Theater in the Harlem neighborhood of Manhattan. Williams discusses attending church at the Abyssinian Baptist Church in Harlem. Williams talks about the sense of fellowship he felt at this predominantly African American church congregation. He discusses working for the Merchant Marine and how the Seafarers' International Union of North America, Atlantic, Gulf, Lakes, and Inland Waters District helped to improve working conditions over the years.
    Duration: 46:55.
  - Wolfish, Aaron, 1993 May 19; 478458 (Box 14, Cassette 91, Box 1, Folder 114, Box 5, Cd 28)
    Aaron Wolfish was born in 1914 in Poland. He immigrated to the United States with his family in 1920. His family was Jewish and he had two brothers. His father worked as a tailor and died in 1929. His mother managed the household. Wolfish attended Public School 147 in the LES and Stuyvesant High School in Manhattan. He worked as clerk in a grocery store and was married.
    This interview was conducted on May 19, 1993 by Helen Goodman at Aaron Wolfish's home in Brooklyn, New York. The interview covers Wolfish's life in the Lower East Side (LES) neighborhood of Manhattan. Wolfish describes his family's apartments in the LES, including the layouts of the apartments, amenities and utilities in the apartments, and the living arrangements. He discusses public baths and public swimming pools he would use on Rutgers Place and Rivington Street in the LES. He discusses illnesses and home remedies in his family. He discusses suicides in his neighborhood, including the death of one of his friends by suicide. He discusses his education, the schools he attended, and anecdotes from his time at school. He discusses traditions in his family around the Jewish holidays, in particular food his mother and wife would make. He describes settlement houses at which he would participate in programs and events, in particular the White Door Settlement on Clinton Street in the LES. Other topics include his after school job of selling newspapers, the Yiddish theatre, and games he would play with his friends in the street.
    Duration: 60:09
  - Zuckerman, Natalie, 1994 February 22; 478475 (Box 15, Cassette 108A-108B, Box 1, Folder 115, Box 6, Cd 8-9)
    Natalie Zuckerman was born into a Jewish family on May 7, 1915 on Essex Street in the Lower East Side (LES) neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. She had three siblings. Her parents immigrated to the United States from Austria, her father when he was 11 years old and her mother when she was a teenager. Zuckerman's father worked as a window cleaner. Zuckerman lived in several apartments in the LES on Ludlow Street, Norfolk Street, Eldridge Street, and Second Avenue.
    This interview was conducted on February 22, 1994 by Kevin Murphy in Brooklyn, New York. The majority of the interview covers Natalie Zuckerman's childhood and Jewish family life in the Lower East Side neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. She discusses her mother's determination to become a United States citizen and recalls her mother attending night school at the Henry Street Settlement in the LES and accompanying her mother to her citizenship test in 1929. Zuckerman describes attending shows at Yiddish theaters on Second Avenue, occasionally purchasing French chocolates at an ice cream parlor on Second Avenue and spending time in the public library. She recalls frequently shopping for fresh food and dry goods with her mother on Orchard Street. Zuckerman relates a detailed story about witnessing her mother having her fortune read in the LES. She recalls her extended family living in the LES and spending the Saturdays together in celebration of the Sabbath. She discusses the types of food the family would prepare together, like potato pancakes topped with sour cream or applesauce. Zuckerman recalls taking dance lessons at the University Settlement House in the LES and accounts a special occasion when Eleanor Roosevelt acted as the dance instructor one evening. She states that after the death of her husband she had started writing her memoir.
    Duration: 2:01:21
  - Zweibach, Rose Halpern, 1993 April 28; 478459 (Box 1, Folder 116, Box 14, Cassette 92, Box 5, Cd 29)
    Rose Halpern Zweibach was born in 1918 in the Lower East Side (LES) neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. Her family was Jewish and she had one brother. Her father immigrated to the United States (US) from Poland and worked as an egg candler, a fruit peddler, and a janitor. Her mother immigrated to the US from Austria-Hungary and worked as a fur operator and a house cleaner. Zweibach graduated from Lehman College in the Bronx and worked as a teacher. She was a member of the Workmen's Circle, Branch 1002 and United Federation of Teachers. She was married and had two daughters.
    This interview was conducted on April 28, 1993 by Annette Franklin at Rose Halpern Zweibach's apartment in the Lower East Side (LES) neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. The interview covers Zweibach's early life in the LES and her family. Zweibach describes the apartments in which her family lived in the LES, the amenities and utilities, the layouts, the living arrangements, and the ways in which the family members negotiated privacy for themselves. She describes her relationship with her brother, in particular her resentment of him when they were children and their relationship at the time of the interview. She discusses her father's jobs, including losing his work as an egg candler when machines were introduced to do that work, and his work as an unskilled laborer in various temporary jobs. She discusses her family's finances while her father could not find permanent work, her parents becoming janitors in one of the buildings in which they lived, and the shame of having to receive home relief benefits during the Great Depression. She recounts gaining a job as a summer school teacher in the Jamaica neighborhood of Queens through the Works Progress Administration. She describes her mother, including her relationship with her brothers and her feminism, which Zweibach credits for her receiving a college education and becoming a professional. Other topics include her jealousy over her brother's religious education, her love of the public library and reading, and her membership in the Workmen's Circle in Manhattan.
    Duration: 1:31:18
- Series II. 1995 Oral History Class Interviews, 1.4 Linear Feet in 2 half manuscript boxes, 1 media box, and 2 card catalog drawers.; 2 videocassettes (vhs); 1 videocassettes (hi8); 3 videodiscs (dvd); 35 audiocassettes; 47 sound discs (cd)
  The interviews in this series were conducted by graduate students enrolled in the oral history class taught by Rachel Bernstein in the New York University Department of History in 1995. The students made contacts through the Museum of the History of New York in the East Harlem neighborhood of Manhattan, New York; Seward Park High School in the Lower East Side neighborhood of Manhattan; and Debra Bernhardt of the Tamiment Library & Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives in the NYU Libraries.
  This series contains interviews conducted by students in Rachel Bernstein's 1995 Oral History class. The narrators include residents of the East Harlem neighborhood of Manhattan, New York; Asian American activists; Central American, African, and Caribbean immigrants who settled in New York City in the 1980s and 1990s; members of the Three Arrows Cooperative Society in Putnam Valley, New York; and residents of public and cooperative housing in the Lower East Side neighborhood of Manhattan. The narrators who lived in East Harlem were members of the East Harlem Protestant Parish, stickball players, or were involved with the Young Lords activist organization. The East Harlem Protestant Parish interviews cover the founding of the church and its work in East Harlem. The stickball interviews contain discussions of different forms of stickball popular in East Harlem through the 1940s and 1960s and amateur and professional stickball teams in New York City from the 1940s to the time of the interview. The interviews conducted with Asian American activists cover their participation in political and social movements, including Asian Americans for Action, Harlem Parents' Committee, and the Organization on African American Unity. These interviews include discussions of the narrators' experiences in the internment camps in the western United States (US) during World War II and of discrimination. The interviews with Central American, African, and Caribbean immigrants include discussions of immigration experiences, comparisons of life in the US and the narrators' countries of origins, and discrimination experienced by the narrators in the US. The majority of the Central American narrators were Nicaraguan or lived in Nicaragua in the 1970s and 1980s, and relate their experiences of the Nicaraguan Revolution between 1979 and 1990. The members of the Three Arrows Cooperative Society (3A) in Putnam Valley, New York describe the community and its principles and their participation other political and social organizations, including the Young People's Socialist League and the Workmen's Circle. The Young Lords interviews discuss the history and activities of the organization in New York City in the 1970s and 1980s.
  This series is arranged in alphabetical order by subject groupings determined by the student interviewers. Within each subject group, the interviews are arranged in alphabetical order by last name of the narrator.
  - Asian American Activist Interviews, 1995
    - Akiya, Karl, 1995 October 20; cuid154; 478489 (Box 15, Cassette 128, Box 1, Folder 117, Box Access Audio 2, Cd 21-22)
      Karl Akiya was born in San Francisco, California in 1909. His father was a chef from Yokohama, Japan who immigrated to the United States (US) in order to learn how to cook American food. Akiya's mother immigrated to the US from Japan after her marriage was arranged with Akiya's father. Akiya was the oldest of three children, and had one brother and one sister. His parents sent Akiya and his siblings to Japan for their education in 1915. Akiya returned to the US in 1932, giving up his dual Japanese citizenship, in order to escape being drafted into the Japanese Army. During World War II he was interned at the Topaz War Relocation Camp in Utah. Akiya worked at two banks, the Office of Strategic Services, a furniture store, and at the University of Michigan as a Japanese teacher. In 1987, Akiya received the Martin Luther King, Jr. Award for Community Organizing.